

PHD CANDIDATE | SESSIONAL LECTURER | RESEARCH SOFTWARE ENGINEER

School of Mathematics and Physics, The University of Queensland

■daniel@vfryer.com | Adanielvfryer.com | frycast | Jefrycast

I specialise in making complex models more transparent, understandable and explainable. It's fascinating that statistics is used in every industry and scientific field, but so much of it is unintuitive and misinterpreted. I've recently been publishing papers on new machine learning methods, and applying them to a number of impactful real-world problems. To make my research accessible, I write useful software packages and libraries in R, Python and Julia. I serve as a council member and Early Career and Student Statisticians' Representative at the Statistical Society of Australia.

Education _

The University of Queensland

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

PhD | Statistics and Mathematics

2019-Current

2014-2018

• Explaining, exploring and clustering with non-linear and complex data

La Trobe University

Bachelor of Science | Mathematics and Statistics with First Class Honours (Weighted Average Mark: 97)

Melbourne, VIC, AU

· Random fields: Long memory, and R for cosmology

Experience_

The University of Queensland

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

CASUAL INSTRUCTOR | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2020-Current

• Master's of Data Science project support

University of Auckland

Auckland, Auckland Region, NZ

SHORT COURSE CREATOR | NEW ZEALAND SOCIAL STATISTICS NETWORK

2018-Current

• Introduction to SQL for academics and professionals

La Trobe University

Melbourne, VIC, AU

SESSIONAL LECTURER | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS

2018-Current

• Master's level meta-analysis | Master's level database fundamentals

The University of Queensland

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2019-2019

2018-2019

• Digital phenotyping for transdiagnostic clustering and psychiatric prognosis

La Trobe University

RESEARCH SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

Melbourne, VIC, AU

• Spherical data analysis in R on the HEALPix grid

Service

Statistical Society of Australia

Melbourne, VIC, AU

 ${\tt Council\ Member\ |\ Early\ Career\ and\ Student\ Statisticians'\ Representative}$

2020-Current

Dimension Reduction and Meta Analysis Research Group

Melbourne, VIC, AU

Member | Website Maintainer

Campus Consultancy

2017-Current

Melbourne, VIC, AU

SENIOR MENTOR AND FOUNDING MEMBER

2017-2019

Research School on Statistics and Data Science

Melbourne, VIC, AU

Journal of Open Source Software

2019–2019

PEER REVIEWER (1 ARTICLE)

PEER REVIEWER (3 ARTICLES)

2019-2019

Melbourne, VIC, AU

Victorian State Emergency Services EMERGENCY FIRST RESPONDER	Melbourne, VIC, AU 2017–2018
La Trobe University Mathematics and Statistics Society	Melbourne, VIC, AU
VICE PRESIDENT NEWSLETTER EDITOR	2016–2016
In2Science	Melbourne, VIC, AU
MENTOR MATHEMATICS SCHOOL OUTREACH	2015–2015
Awards	
Three Minute Thesis People's Choice	Saint Lucia, QLD, AU
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, SCHOOL OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS	2020
Pitching Research Competition Best Written and Oral Pitch University-Wide	Saint Lucia, QLD, AU
THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, BUSINESS SCHOOL	2019
Pro Vice Chancellor's Commendation (awarded four times)	Melbourne, VIC, AU
La Trobe University, University-Wide	2018
Department Prize in Fourth Year Statistics Best Performing Student La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	Melbourne, VIC, AU 2018
David Myer's Medallion La Trobe's most prestigious undergraduate award	Melbourne, VIC, AU
LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, COLLEGE OF SCIENCE, HEALTH AND ENGINEERING	2018
Silver Scholarship Community Involvement and Dedication to Mathematics	Melbourne, VIC, AL
La Trobe University Student Union, University-Wide	201
Department Prize in Third Year Statistics Best Performing Student	Melbourne, VIC, AL
La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	2016
Prof CJ Eliezer Prize in Second Year Mathematics Best Performing Student	Melbourne, VIC, AL
La Trobe University, Department of Mathematics and Statistics	2015
Prof Jim Morrison Prize in Chemistry Best Performing Student (awarded twice)	Melbourne, VIC, AL
La Trobe University, School of Molecular Sciences	2014
La Trobe Award in Community Engagement Volunteer Efforts	Melbourne, VIC, AL
La Trobe University, University-Wide	2014
Publications	
Pipeline	
D Fryer, I Strumke, H Nguyen	arXiv
SHAPLEY VALUE CONFIDENCE INTERVALS FOR VARIABLE SELECTION IN REGRESSION MODELS	2020
D Fryer, H Nguyen, P Castellazzi	arXiv
K-MEANS ON A LOG-CHOLESKY MANIFOLD, WITH UNSUPERVISED CLASSIFICATION OF RADAR PRODUCTS	2020
HD Nguyen, DV Fryer	arXiv
A BINARY-RESPONSE REGRESSION MODEL BASED ON SUPPORT VECTOR MACHINES	2020
D Fryer, I Strümke, H Nguyen Explaining the data or explaining a model? Shapley values that uncover non-linear dependencies	arXiv 2020
D Fryer, M Li, A Olenko RCOSMO: R PACKAGE FOR ANALYSIS OF SPHERICAL, HEALPIX AND COSMOLOGICAL DATA	arXiv 2015
Published	
D Fryer, H Nguyen, P Orban	Journal of Open Source Software
STUDENTLIFE: TIDY HANDLING AND NAVIGATION OF A VALUABLE MOBILE-HEALTH DATASET	2019
D. Francis A. Olanda	Research School on Statistics and
D Fryer, A Olenko	Data Science
Control Devil Co	0046

Spherical Data Handling and Analysis with R package RCOSMO

2019

Presentations _____

UQ Research Video Pitch	St Lucia
FORECASTING PSYCHIATRIC SYMPTOMS WITH DIGITAL PHENOTYPING	2020
First prize. youtu.be/h-m8QwLq29Y	
UQ Three Minute Thesis Presentation	St Lucia
MACHINE LEARNING: THE BIG BLACK BOX	2020
People's choice award. vimeo.com/434959101	
RSSDS2019 Poster Presentation	Melbourne
Spherical Data Handling and Analysis with R package rcosmo	2019
Poster and Springer book chapter	
UseR!2018 Conference	Brisbane
COSMIC MICROWAVE BACKGROUND DATA ANALYSIS WITH R	2018
R package published on CRAN. https://youtu.be/7KBsguOlEHs	
Australian Mathematical Sciences Institute Summer Research School	Melbourne
FUNCTIONALS OF LONG-RANGE DEPENDENT FIELDS AND HERMITE DISTRIBUTIONS	2017
Summer Research Scholarship recipient. vrs.amsi.org.au/daniel-vidali-fryer-2017/	
UNSW Statistical Challenges in Astronomy	Sydney
LIGHTING TALK: A NEW R PACKAGE FOR COSMOLOGY	2017
Fostering new collaborations in statistics and astronomy	